A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Douglas Ensminger Oral History FA744
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Douglas Ensminger Oral History
1971-1973
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ensminger, Douglas, 1910-1989
Ford Foundation
FA744
1 Cubic Feet
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Material more than ten years old is open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
All restrictions on access to and use of this collection have lapsed, and exclusive rights at this time belong to the Ford Foundation.
Biographical / Historical
Douglas Ensminger served as Representative of the Ford Foundation in India from 1952-1970, and formally retired from the Foundation on December 16, 1970 to accept an appointment as professor of rural sociology at University of Missouri. At the time of his retirement, according to Ensminger, he was asked by the Trustees to record his reminiscences of his work and the Foundation's programs in India. He dictated his reminiscences about his time in India while in Columbia, working with two assistants paid for by the Foundation. He worked on the project between 1971 and 1973, which coincided with the Foundation's own oral history project. Although Ensminger did not formally participate in the oral history project, he did consult with Charles Morrissey and Ron Grele, the oral history project staff, and he did execute an agreement with the Foundation regarding rights to his material.
Scope and Contents
Oral history.
Arrangement
Arranged in 3 series: 1. Topics related to Non-Project Areas. 2. Topics related to Specific Project Areas. 3. Programs in Pakistan and Nepal.
India; Ford Foundation -- History; Ford Foundation
- Topics Related to Non-Project Areas, 1971-1972; A
  - A.1 Introduction (Box 1)
  - A.2 The Ford Foundation's Relations with the Department of Economic Affairs, Ministry of Finance [Government of India], October 19, 1971 (Box 1)
  - A.3 The Ford Foundation's Relations with the [Government of India] Planning Commission, October 21, 1971 (Box 1)
  - A.4 Why were so many grants made to the Government of India instead of Non-government Agencies and Institutions, October 27, 1971 (Box 1)
  - A.5 The delicacy of the Ford Foundation's Relationships with other Foreign Aid giving agencies working in India, November 15, 1971 (Box 1)
  - A.6 The Ford Foundation' relations with the Center and State Government in India., November 16, 1971 (Box 1)
  - A.7 The Foundation's objectives and reasons for its presence in India, November 18, 1971 (Box 1)
  - A.8 Relationships with Prime Minister Jawaharlal Nehru, November 29, 1971 (Box 1)
  - A.9 The significance of maintaining relations with the [Government of India] Cabinet, December 10, 1971 (Box 1)
  - A.10 The significance of relations with India's Presidents., December 13, 1971 (Box 1)
  - A.11 Keeping in touch with all key points in India's Central Government power structure when advancing and discussing new ideas, December 14, 1971 (Box 1)
  - A.12 The importance of understanding India's foreign policy to the Foundation's operations in India. (Box 1)
  - A.13 Need for understanding the Gandhian Philosophy and different interpretations expounded by Gandhian followers., December 16, 1971 (Box 1)
  - A.14 Why an understanding of India's Caste System was important to the Ford Foundation's working in India, December 27, 1971 (Box 1)
  - A.15 How were the relations defined between the Ford Foundation as an American institution working in India and the American Embassy, April 18, 1972 (Box 1)
  - A.16 Why were there so few foreign institutional contracts to backstop Ford Foundation supported programs in India, April 19, 1972 (Box 1)
  - A.17 In what ways did the CIA [Central Intelligence Agency] issues effect the Ford Foundation's work in its relations in India, May 9, 1972 (Box 1)
  - A.18 What considerations went into formulating policies for housing accommodation of Foundation's foreign staff living in India, May 10, 1972 (Box 1)
  - A.19 The importance to the Foundation's recruitment in having the American International School, the Inter-denominational Church and the Holy Family Hospital., May 11, 1972 (Box 1)
  - A.20 The significance of major economic, climatic, social and political crises in India to opening the doors for major changes, May 12, 1972 (Box 1)
  - A.21 Importance of understanding the time and process for significant change to take place, May 23, 1972 (Box 1)
  - A.22 The problems involved on India's side in assigning creative people to give leadership to new and innovative programs, May 24, 1972 (Box 1)
  - A.23 The pros and cons of putting the maximum amount of Ford Foundation funds for India into grants in contrast to contributing to the maximum through high level staff in discussing ideas, examining alternatives and backing up India to give leadership to change and development as well as assist in starting new programs. (Where does the money go?), May 30, 1972 (Box 1)
  - A.24 Too much emphasis on Indian counterparts to match foreign consultants and too little concern on India's part in maximizing utilization of consultants, May 31, 1972 (Box 1)
  - A.25 The pros and cons of Ford Foundation grant funds applying to both rupee and dollars costs, June 1, 1972 (Box 1)
  - A.26 The problems of assisting non-government organizations, agencies and institutions and the problem of these non-government institutions becoming viable, June 5, 1972 (Box 1)
  - A.27 Helping people locked in poverty, June 16, 1972 (Box 1)
  - A.28 The pros and cons of the Ford Foundation making greater use of Indians as consultants in India, June 19, 1972 (Box 1)
  - A.29 India's policy and practice of frequent transfer of key staff made the task of starting new programs exceedingly difficult, June 19, 1972 (Box 1)
  - A.30 The performance payoff of sending Indian officials abroad for short term training is marginal and of questionable value, June 19, 1972 (Box 1)
  - A.31 How did the Foundation function in its administrative services as it grew and functioned during the decade of the Fifties and Sixties, June 19, 1972 (Box 1)
  - A.32 The western orientation to time and quality of performance comes in the way of the working of program advisors and consultants in India, June 22, 1972 (Box 1)
  - A.33 The Ford Foundation has a fetish about evaluation of projects and programs it assists with but shows little evidence of drawing on documented evidence, June 26, 1972 (Box 1)
  - A.34 The Government of India and non-government agencies and organizations' accountability for Ford Foundation grant funds, June 29, 1972 (Box 1)
  - A.35 The interaction between the Ford Foundation's India Field Office and New York office, June 30, 1972 (Box 1)
  - A.36 The advantages and disadvantages to the Ford Foundation's India office in using the Institute of International Education, New York to administer fellowships, travel and study awards, and contract employees, July 6, 1972 (Box 1)
  - A.37 The importance of having a strategy for introducing change, October 25, 1972 (Box 1)
  - A.38 Recruiting program advisors and consultants, October 25, 1972 (Box 1)
  - A.39 The "Little People" of India, November 6, 1972 (Box 1)
  - A.40 The Ford Foundation's Image in India, November 7, 1972 (Box 1)
  - A.41 The growth of the Ford Foundation's India Headquarters Office, November 17, 1972 (Box 1)
  - A.42 Recollections and Reminiscences (Box 1)
  - A.43 The Ensminger family's experience in India (Box 1)
- Topics Related to Specific Projects, 1971-1972; B
  - B.1 The Ford Foundation's early and continuous concern about population and family (Box 2)
  - B.2 The Ford Foundation's contribution in the field of India's village and small industries, November 5, 1971 (Box 2)
  - B.3 The Ford Foundation's persistent concern and role in assisting India achieve a status of food enough for its people, January 5, 1972 (Box 2)
  - B.4 Why did the Ford Foundation accept and respond to Dr. B.C. Roy's invitation to assist in the development of a long range plan for the Greater Calcutta Area?, February 7, 1972 (Box 2)
  - B.5 Why did the Ford Foundation assist with India's handicrafts and handloom industry, February 9, 1972 (Box 2)
  - B.6 The Ford Foundation's involvement in public administration, February 11, 1972 (Box 2)
  - B.7 The Ford Foundation and management education in India, March 2, 1972 (Box 2)
  - B.8 The historical basis of the Foundation's involvement in strengthening India's institutional competence in economics, March 29, 1972 (Box 2)
  - B.9 Why did the Ford Foundation get involved in training five hundred of India's young engineers in steel making, April 24, 1972 (Box 2)
  - B.10 The Ford Foundation's support to the Delhi Center for the Orientation of Foreigners taking up with assignments in India, May 18, 1972 (Box 2)
  - B.11 The Ford Foundation's support and withdrawal from the Center for Applied Politics, June 19, 1972 (Box 2)
  - B.12 The sensitivity of the Ford Foundation contributing to India's art and cultural programs, June 21, 1972 (Box 2)
  - B.13 India's problem of Brain Drain and the Ford Foundation's efforts to counteract it, June 23, 1972 (Box 2)
  - B.14 Ford Foundation's contribution to India in educational television and mass communications, June 23, 1972 (Box 2)
  - B.15 The Ford Foundation involvement and contribution in the field of law and legal education in India, June 23, 1972 (Box 2)
  - B.16 The Ford Foundation's Role in assisting India in its Manpower, June 26, 1972 (Box 2)
  - B.17 The Ford Foundation involvement and contribution in the field of law and legal education in India, June 23, 1972 (Box 2)
  - B. 18 The Ford Foundation's early interest and involvement in Home Economics of work in India, July 5, 1972 (Box 2)
  - B.19 The Ford Foundation's interest and assistance in the development of the sociological sciences in India, July 10, 1972 (Box 2)
  - B.20 Why did the Ford Foundation get involved in helping India make a go of nationalizing its Banks, July 11, 1972 (Box 2)
  - B.21 The Ford Foundation's nineteen years of involvement with India's Community Development Program, July 11, 1972 (Box 2)
  - B.22 The Leigh Stevens village electric and water project, August 21, 1972 (Box 2)
  - B.23 The Ford Foundation's interest and involvement in Indian Education, August 23, 1972 (Box 2)
  - B.24 Williams College and Harvard University Public Service Fellowship program, November 6, 1972 (Box 2)
- Programs in Pakistan and Nepal, 1972; C
  - C.1 The Ford Foundation's involvement in Pakistan, 1951-1953., September 22, 1972 (Box 2)
  - C.2 The Ford Foundation's contributions to Nepal, September 22, 1972 (Box 2)